I'm an underwater explorer,
أنا مستكشفة ما تحت الماء،
more specifically a cave diver.
وبشكل أكثر تحديدًا غطاسة كهوف.
I wanted to be an astronaut when I was a little kid,
أردت أن أكون رائدة فضاء عندما كنت فتاة صغيرة،
but growing up in Canada as a young girl, that wasn't really available to me.
ولكن لنشأتي في كندا كفتاة شابة، لم يكن ذلك حقا متاحًا بالنسبة لي.
But as it turns out, we know a lot more about space
ولكن كما اتضح، نحن نعرف عن الفضاء أكثر
than we do about the underground waterways coursing through our planet,
مما نعرف عن الممرات المائية الجوفية في كوكبنا،
the very lifeblood of Mother Earth.
شريان الحياة في الأرض.
So I decided to do something that was even more remarkable.
لذلك قررت أن أفعل شيئا ملحوظًا أكثر.
Instead of exploring outer space,
بدلا من استكشاف الفضاء الخارجي،
I wanted to explore the wonders of inner space.
أردت أن أستكشف عجائب الفضاء الداخلي.
Now, a lot of people will tell you
سيقول لك الكثيرون
that cave diving is perhaps one of the most dangerous endeavors.
أن الغوص قي الكهوف أحد أكثر المساعي خطورة.
I mean, imagine yourself here in this room,
أعني، تخيل نفسك هنا في هذه الغرفة،
if you were suddenly plunged into blackness,
لو أنك دخلت فجأة في ظلام،
with your only job to find the exit,
ووظيفتك الوحيدة هي إيجاد المخرج،
sometimes swimming through these large spaces,
في بعض الأحيان سِباحةً خلال هذه المساحات الكبيرة،
and at other times crawling beneath the seats,
و في أحيانٍ أخرى زحفًا تحت المقاعد،
following a thin guideline,
متتبعاً خطاً توجيهياً رفيعاً،
just waiting for the life support to provide your very next breath.
منتظرًا فقط دعم الحياة لتوفير نفسك التالي.
Well, that's my workplace.
هذا هو مكان عملي.
But what I want to teach you today
ولكن ما أريد أن أعلمه لكم اليوم
is that our world is not one big solid rock.
هو أن عالمنا ليس صخرة واحدة صلبة و كبيرة.
It's a whole lot more like a sponge.
إنه شبيه أكثر بالإسفنجة.
I can swim through a lot of the pores in our earth's sponge,
يمكنني السباحة خلال الكثير من مسام إسفنجة أرضنا،
but where I can't,
ولكن حيث لا أستطيع الوصول،
other life-forms and other materials can make that journey without me.
تقوم بتلك الرحلة كائنات أخرى بدوني.
And my voice is the one that's going to teach you
وصوتي هو ما سوف يعلمك
about the inside of Mother Earth.
عن ما بداخل أمّنا الأرض.
There was no guidebook available to me
لم يكن هناك دليل ارشادي متاحًا لي
when I decided to be the first person to cave dive inside Antarctic icebergs.
حين قررت أن أكون أول شخص يغوص الكهوف داخل الجبال الجليدية في أنتارتيكا.
In 2000, this was the largest moving object on the planet.
في عام 2000، كان هذا أكبر جسم متحرك على الكوكب.
It calved off the Ross Ice Shelf,
انفصل قبالة الجرف الجليدي روس،
and we went down there to explore ice edge ecology
وذهبنا الى هناك لاستكشاف بيئة حافة الجليد
and search for life-forms beneath the ice.
والبحث عن أشكال الحياة تحت الجليد.
We use a technology called rebreathers.
نستخدم تقنية تسمى "rebreathers".
It's an awful lot like the same technology that is used for space walks.
انها تشبه التكنولوجيا التي تستخدم للسير في الفضاء.
This technology enables us to go deeper
هذه التكنولوجيا تمكننا من التعمق
than we could've imagined even 10 years ago.
أكثر مما كان يمكن أن نتصور قبل 10 أعوام.
We use exotic gases,
نحن نستخدم الغازات الغريبة،
and we can make missions even up to 20 hours long underwater.
ويمكننا أن نقوم ببعثات تصل إلى 20 ساعة تحت الماء.
I work with biologists.
أنا أعمل مع علماء الأحياء.
It turns out that caves are repositories of amazing life-forms,
اتضح أن الكهوف هي مستودعات من أشكال الحياة المذهلة،
species that we never knew existed before.
أنواع لم نعرف بوجودها من قبل.
Many of these life-forms live in unusual ways.
العديد من هذه المخلوقات تعيش بطرق غير عادية.
They have no pigment and no eyes in many cases,
ليس لديهم لون ولا عيون في كثير من الحالات،
and these animals are also extremely long-lived.
وهذه الحيوانات أيضا تعيش طويلًا.
In fact, animals swimming in these caves today
في الواقع، الحيوانات التي تسبح في هذه الكهوف اليوم
are identical in the fossil record
متطابقة في السجل الأحفوري
that predates the extinction of the dinosaurs.
الذي يسبق انقراض الديناصورات.
So imagine that: these are like little swimming dinosaurs.
لذلك تصور هذا: هذه الكائنات مثل ديناصورات سابحة صغيرة.
What can they teach us about evolution and survival?
ماذا يمكن أن تعلمنا عن التطور والبقاء على قيد الحياة؟
When we look at an animal like this remipede swimming in the jar,
عندما ننظر إلى حيوان مثل هذا الذي يسبح في الجرة،
he has giant fangs with venom.
لديه أنياب عملاقة سامة.
He can actually attack something 40 times his size and kill it.
يمكنه أن يهاجم شيئا أكبر منه 40 مرة وقتله.
If he were the size of a cat,
لو كان بحجم قط،
he'd be the most dangerous thing on our planet.
لكان أكثر شيء خطورة على كوكبنا.
And these animals live in remarkably beautiful places,
وهذه الحيوانات تعيش في أماكن جميلة بشكل ملحوظ،
and in some cases, caves like this, that are very young,
وفي بعض الأحيان، كهوف حديثة جدًا مثل هذه،
yet the animals are ancient.
إلا أنها حيوانات عتيقة.
How did they get there?
كيف وصلوا إلى هناك؟
I also work with physicists,
أنا أعمل ايضا مع علماء الفيزياء،
and they're interested oftentimes in global climate change.
وهم في كثير من الأحيان مهتمون بتغير المناخ العالمي.
They can take rocks within the caves,
يمكن أن يأخذوا الصخور التي بداخل الكهوف،
and they can slice them and look at the layers within with rocks,
ويمكن أن يقطعوها ويلقوا نظرة على الطبقات التي بداخل الحجارة،
much like the rings of a tree,
مثل حلقات الشجرة،
and they can count back in history
و يمكنهم الرجوع إلى الماضي
and learn about the climate on our planet at very different times.
والتعرف على مناخ كوكبنا في أوقات مختلفة.
The red that you see in this photograph
الأحمر الذي ترونه في هذه الصورة
is actually dust from the Sahara Desert.
هو في الواقع غبار من الصحراء الكبرى.
So it's been picked up by wind, blown across the Atlantic Ocean.
تم التقاطه بواسطة الرياح، في مهب عبر المحيط الأطلسي.
It's rained down in this case on the island of Abaco in the Bahamas.
أمطرت عليه في هذه الحالة في جزيرة أباكو في جزر البهاماس.
It soaks in through the ground
يتسرب خلال الأرض
and deposits itself in the rocks within these caves.
ويوضع في الصخور داخل هذه الكهوف.
And when we look back in the layers of these rocks, we can find times
وعندما ننظر في طبقات هذه الصخور، يمكننا أن نجد مرات
when the climate was very, very dry on earth,
عندما كان المناخ جافًا جدًا على الأرض،
and we can go back many hundreds of thousands of years.
ويمكننا أن نعود مئات الآلاف من السنين.
Paleoclimatologists are also interested
علماء المناخ أيضا مهتمون
in where the sea level stands were at other times on earth.
بأين بلغ مستوى سطح البحر في أحيان أخرى على وجه الأرض.
Here in Bermuda, my team and I embarked
هنا في برمودا، شرعت أنا و فريقي
on the deepest manned dives ever conducted in the region,
في أعمق رحلة غوص أجريت في المنطقة،
and we were looking for places
وكنا نبحث عن أماكن
where the sea level used to lap up against the shoreline,
حيث وصل مستوى سطح البحر إلى الشاطئ،
many hundreds of feet below current levels.
أقل عدة مئات من الأقدام من المستويات الحالية.
I also get to work with paleontologists and archaeologists.
أعمل أيضا مع علماء الحفريات وعلماء الآثار.
In places like Mexico, in the Bahamas, and even in Cuba,
في أماكن مثل المكسيك، وجزر البهاماس، وحتى في كوبا،
we're looking at cultural remains and also human remains in caves,
نبحث عن بقايا ثقافية وكذلك بقايا الإنسان في الكهوف،
and they tell us a lot
ويخبروننا بالكثير
about some of the earliest inhabitants of these regions.
عن بعض من أقدم سكان هذه المناطق.
But my very favorite project of all was over 15 years ago,
ولكن مشروعي المفضل كان قبل أكثر من 15 عاما،
when I was a part of the team that made the very first
عندما كنت جزءا من الفريق الذي قدم أول
accurate, three-dimensional map of a subterranean surface.
خريطة دقيقة ثلاثية الأبعاد لسطح جوفي.
This device that I'm driving through the cave
هذا الجهاز الذي كنت أقوده خلال الكهف
was actually creating a three-dimensional model as we drove it.
كان في الواقع يخلق نموذج ثلاثي الأبعاد بينما نقوده.
We also used ultra low frequency radio
كما استخدمنا الراديو ذات التردد المنخفض جدا
to broadcast back to the surface our exact position within the cave.
لنبث إلى السطح موضعنا الدقيق داخل الكهف.
So I swam under houses and businesses and bowling alleys and golf courses,
لقد سبحت تحت المنازل والشركات وممرات البولينغ وملاعب الغولف،
and even under a Sonny's BBQ Restaurant,
وحتى تحت مطعم Sonny's BBQ،
Pretty remarkable, and what that taught me
لافت للنظر جدا، وعلمني هذا
was that everything we do on the surface of our earth
أن كل ما نقوم به على سطح أرضنا
will be returned to us to drink.
سوف يُعاد لنا لنشربه.
Our water planet is not just rivers, lakes and oceans,
كوكبنا من المياه ليس فقط الأنهار والبحيرات والمحيطات،
but it's this vast network of groundwater that knits us all together.
ولكن هذه الشبكة الواسعة من المياه الجوفية التي تحوكنا جميعا سويًا.
It's a shared resource from which we all drink.
انها مورد مشترك نشرب منه جميعاً.
And when we can understand our human connections with our groundwater
وعندما نتمكن من فهم اتصال الإنسان مع مياهنا الجوفية
and all of our water resources on this planet,
وجميع مواردنا المائية على هذا الكوكب،
then we'll be working on the problem
حينها سنكون نعمل على حل المشكلة
that's probably the most important issue of this century.
التي هي على الأرجح أهم قضية في هذا القرن.
So I never got to be that astronaut that I always wanted to be,
لم أتمكن من أن أكون رائدة الفضاء التي أردت دائما أن أكون،
but this mapping device, designed by Dr. Bill Stone, will be.
ولكن جهاز رسم الخرائط هذا، الذي صممه الدكتور بيل ستون، سيكون.
It's actually morphed.
لقد تحول فعلا.
It's now a self-swimming autonomous robot,
إنه الآن إنسان آلي يسبح مستقلًا،
artificially intelligent,
يمتلك ذكاء اصطناعي،
and its ultimate goal is to go to Jupiter's moon Europa
وهدفه الذهاب الى قمرالمشتري يوروبا
and explore oceans beneath the frozen surface of that body.
واستكشاف المحيطات تحت السطح المتجمد لذلك الجسم.
And that's pretty amazing.
وهذا مدهش للغاية.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)